Guide to the Mauritius Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Mauritius collection
1831-2001
1950-1996
MS 1531
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.77
(3 boxes)
The collection consists of manuscripts and printed material relating to the history of Mauritius and current political, economic, and social conditions in Mauritius.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
African Collection, MS 605; Pamphlet Collection, MS 1351; African Postcard Collection, MS 1575. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The material in the original accession is arranged by category and chronologically therein. Additions to the collection may vary in arrangement.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of manuscripts and printed material relating to the history of Mauritius and current political, economic, and social conditions in Mauritius.
Women -- Mauritius; Mauritius -- Description and travel; Mauritius -- Economic conditions; Mauritius -- Politics and government
- Inventory
  - Journals: cultural and educational, 1950, 1976-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Mauritius Police Magazine, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Periodicals: magazines; newspapers; popular journals, 1981-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General information pamphlets; brochures; booklets, 1950, 1981-1982, 1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Women's movement/organizations: journals; newsletters; printed material, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photograph, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Additional Material, 1831-1996; Accession 1995-M-194
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged by type and chronologically therein.
  - General information brochures, 1981, 1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Government documents
    Scope and Contents
    The government documents presented at the various courts include appeals, ratifications and/or amendments of ordinances and orders, and the makeup of the Constitution of the government council.
    - At the Court of Saint James's, 1831 August 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - At the Court at Windsor, 1842 January 15, 1877 July 11, 1879 June 26, 1880 March 18, 1890 November 22, 1894 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - At the Court at Osborne House, Isle of Wight, 1879 February 4, 1885 August 12 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - At the Court at Buckingham Palace, 1905 February 27, 1909 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Government memoranda and reports
    Government memoranda and reports relate to one specific topic, unlike the documents presented at the various courts which cover a multitude of topics.
    - "Report of the Currency Notes Commission, 1935-1936" (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Memorandum on Mauritius Development and Welfare: Ten Year Plan", 1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Memorandum on Social Welfare", 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Social Insurance Schemes in Mauritius", 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Report on Secondary Education in Mauritius, October 1947", 1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The Production of Vegetable Seeds in Mauritius (1943-1946)", 1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Report on the Housing of Sugar Estate Workers", 1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Harbour Guide, 1940", 1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Memorandum on Long Term Policy, Food Production Board", 1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Report of a Committee appointed for the purpose of investigating the Question of relieving the Police Department of Revenue and Liquor Control and of the collection of Direct Taxes and Licences, Sessional Paper No. 1 of 1951, Legislative Council" (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Report of the Committee on the Future of the Sack Factory, Sessional Paper No. 5 of 1951, Legislative Council" (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Report of the Committee appointed to consider the possibility of establishing a Planters" Mechanical Equipment Fund, Sessional Paper No. 6 of 1951, Legislative Council" (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Salaries Commission, Second Interim Report, Cost of Living Allowances, Sessional Paper No. 8 of 1951" (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Cost of Living Allowance, Governor's despatch of 30th May and views of the Secretary of State contained in his telegram of 8th June, Sessional Paper No. 9 of 1951, Legislative Council" (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Report of the Committee appointed to review the conditions governing the payment of Outdoor Relief, Sessional Paper No. 2 of 1952, Legislative Council" (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Liquor Policy of the Mauritius Government, Sessional Paper No. 7 of 1952, Legislative Council" (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Education Officers' Conference 1951: The Road Ahead", 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Historical Monuments of Mauritius", 1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Report on Setting Up a Port Authority, October 1972", 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Mauritius-Resettlement of Persons Transferred From Chagos Archipelago: Visit to Mauritius From 24 January to 2 February", 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Industrial Dispute Between Tyre Retreading Factories Workers' Union and Retreaders Ltd.", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Indian Cultural Review, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Le Nouveau Militant, 1982 February 20 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Two Visits to Rodrigues, 1948 and 1949, with H.E. Sir Hilary Blood, by Alfred North-Coombes, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Voice of Mauritians (official magazine of the Association for the Promotion of the Welfare of Mauritians in the U.K.), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Additional material, 1975-2001; Accession 2015-M-001
  - Printed material, 1975-2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)